Guide to the Jerry C. Debes World War II papers, 1942-1996 MS 579
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jerry C. Debes World War II papers
1942-1996
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Debes, Robert R., DDS
MS 579
0.75 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The collection consists of letters, newspaper clippings, military reports and documents and original photographs, certificates, a small group of callings cards, and memorabilia. The collection focuses on the military career and death of a first generation American pilot, Jerry C. Debes, of Syrian heritage, in the European Theater of World War II and the subsequent efforts of his family to honor his memory.
Biographical / Historical
Jerry C. Debes (1920-1944) was born in Beaumont, Texas as one of five children of immigrant parents. His father Mike N. Debes (b.c. 1881) immigrated to America from Tripoli, Syria (now a part of Lebanon) in 1892. Mike married Vehiba, also Syrian, about 1907 and began his retail business in Beaumont, Texas. The Debes children attended Beaumont High School from which Jerry Debes graduated in 1938. He then attended the local Lamar College to study accounting.
On December 7, 1941, Debes was working as an accountant for the Stedman Wholesale Company. He enlisted in the US Army where he was sent to Camp Crowder, Mo. to be trained for the newly-established Signal Corps for the Second Division of the US Army Air Force (AAF). Preferring to become a pilot, Debes then began training at the Wilson & Bonafils Flying School in Chickasha, Oklahoma but failed to finish the program. He then studied at the bombardier school at the George Air Force base in Victorville, CA. and graduated on July 31, 1943. He did additional training as a bombardier at the Air Force bases in Pueblo, CO and Tuscan, AZ eventually becoming a bombardier instructor. In the spring of 1944, he became certified as an aviation navigator.
Lt. Jerry C. Debes was then transferred to the RAF base in Halesworth, England as part of the 846th Squadron of the 489th Bombardment Group of the Eighth Air Force (8AF). Jerry and his crew christened their B-24 Liberator plane as the "Agony Wagon". Although notorious for catching on fire because of the fuel tank placement, the B-24 Liberator eventually became the most produced American military aircraft in history. The crew of the "Agony Wagon" entered combat on May 30, 1944 at the very end of the Allied Forces' "softening up" process of Nazi-occupied France prior to the D-Day invasion.
The Allied invasion of Normandy began on June 2, 1944. Debes flew six combat missions that focused exclusively on strategic targets such as factories, oil refineries, and airfields. On August 16, 1944, Jerry Debes and crew were on their tenth mission with orders to destroy the Rothensee plant and power stations in Magdeburg, Germany. After dropping their loads, the 846th squadron had turned back towards England when the "Agony Wagon" bombed accidently by another Allied plane. The Debes family received word that Jerry was "missing in action" one week later. Over a year later, the US War Department finally declared Second Lieutenant Jerry C. Debes officially "dead". He was posthumously awarded the US Army's Purple Heart and the USAF Air Medal for his service, and a tombstone in his memory was placed in the Lorraine American Cemetery outside St. Avold (Moselle), France in 1947. His family spent the rest of the decade trying unsuccessfully to discover the circumstances of his death. After visiting his brother's grave in France, Dr. Robert Debes of Houston, Texas reopened the inquiry in 1988.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters, newspaper clippings, military reports and documents and original photographs, certificates, a small group of callings cards, and memorabilia. The collection focuses on the military career and death of a first generation American pilot, Jerry C. Debes, of Syrian heritage, in the European Theater of World War II and the subsequent efforts of his family to honor his memory.
The collection divides itself naturally into two main chronological parts containing several series in each. The first group (1942-1949) is focused on Debes' military career and his family's efforts to discover the circumstances of his death. It also includes materials concerning the Jerry Debes memorial Headstone placed by the American Battle Military Commission in the Lorraine American Cemetery in St. Avold, France. It also includes personal and military–oriented photographs. Other memorabilia are the US Air Force's Air Medal and Purple Heart medal in their respective cases, two copies of Jerry Debes' Purple heart certificates and Jerry Debes' calling cards.
The second part is devoted to the efforts of Dr. Robert Debes to discover the exact circumstances of his brother's death due to friendly fire in late 1980's. It includes Dr. Debes' successful project to have his brother's name listed on the Roll of Honor at the American Memorial Chapel in St. Paul's Cathedral in London, England as well as the donations of materials to the Lone Star flight Museum in Galveston, Texas, the Air Force Historical Research Agency at the Maxwell Air Force Base in Alabama, and Rice University in Houston, Texas.
It is important to note that most of the documents are not original but photographed copies. Original materials are indicated in the Finding Aid. The photographs and memorabilia are all original.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Dr. Robert Debes and Mrs. Beatrice Debes Jamail donated their brother's papers and memorabilia to the Fondren Library in May 2011. All items came from their family collection.
General
Please note the following abbreviations: American Battle Monuments Commission [ABMC]; United States Air Force [USAF].
Related Materials
The Jerry C. Debes display case at the Lone Star Flight Museum in Galveston, Texas. The Jerry C. Debes Collection at the Air Force Historical Research Agency in Maxwell, Alabama.
Index Terms
Subjects
World War (1939-1945)
Document Types
memorabilia; photographs; corrrespondence
- Series I: Jerry Debes Military Career and Death, 1942-1949, 148870
  - Subseries A: Correspondence (1942-1949), 148871
    - Biographical sketch [n.d.], 148872 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter, General H. R. Harmon to Mr. and Mrs. Mike Debes Oct. 15, 1942, 148873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jerry Debes' Last Will and Testament July 8, 1943, 148874 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jerry Debes' General Power of Attorney July 8, 1943, 148875 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Graduation Invitation and calling card July 31, 1943, 159732 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clipping [prob. Beaumont Enterprise, c. 1943] [orig.], 159733 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jerry Debes' Statement of Personal Affairs May 12, 1944, 159734 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Check List for Military Personnel June 18, 1944, 159735 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters (51) Jerry Debes to Family March 11, 1944 – August 15, 1944, 159736 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Address Card for Jerry Debes in Halesworth, England [n.d.], 159737 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Railroad Shipping Receipt for Footlocker June 10, 1944, 159738 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Special Orders, 489th Bombardment Group Station Headquarters July 18, 1944, 159739 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Western Union Telegram War Department to Vahiba Debes August 28, 1944, 159740 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Western Union Telegram Lori Springer to Beatrice Debes August 30, 1944, 159741 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper clipping, Beaumont Enterprise Sept. 3, 1944, 159742 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letter, Gen. Robert Dunlop to Vahiba Debes January 16, 1945, 159743 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letter, Major Gen. Gault to Vahiba Debes Feb. 9, 1945, 159744 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. J. A. Ulio to Vahiba Debes March 19, 1945, 159745 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. Ulio to Vahiba Debes June 8, 1945, 159746 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letter, Elizabeth Knapp to Beatrice Jamail Aug. 31, 1945, 159747 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen Edward Witsell to Beatrice Jamail January 10, 1946, 159748 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. Edward Witsell to Senator Thomas Connally June 4, 1946, 159749 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter, Col. William J. McDonald to Senator Thomas Connelly June 10, 1946, 159750 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letter, Sec. A. S. Carr to Texas U.S. Attorney Steve King June 13, 1946, 159751 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Letter, Attorney Steve King to Mike Debes June 17, 1946, 159752 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - U.S. War Department's Official Death Notification Feb. 18, 1947 [original], 159753 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. Edward Witsell to Mike and Dahiba Debes Feb. 17, 1947, 159754 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letter, Major Richard Coombs to Nicky Debes June 9, 1947, 159755 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Letter, Adj. Gen. Edward Witsell to Nicky Debes July 2, 1947, 159756 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. Thomas Larkin to Mike Debes Oct. 20, 1947, 159757 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letter, Major Richard Coombs to Nickey Debes Jan. 13, 1948, 159758 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Letter, Mike Debes to Quartermaster General Feb. 16, 1948 [notes attached], 159759 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Letter, Maj. Gen. H. Feldman to Mike Debes April 26, 1949, 159760 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - U.S. War Department Brochure March 5, 1945 [orig.], 159761 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Letter, Dr. Robert Debes to Nick about collection preservation & article, 1994-06-14-1994-06-15 (Box 1, Folder 35a)
  - Subseries B: ABMC Documents (1947-1988), 159662
    - ABMC Brochure, "American Cemeteries" [n.d.] [orig, 159663 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - ABMC Description and history of Lorraine American Cemetery [n.d.] [orig.], 159762 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - ABMC map of Lorraine American Cemetery [n.d.] [orig.], 159763 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Description of ceremonial American flag from interment ceremony at the Lorraine American Cemetery [n.d.], 159764 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - ABMC Form #50, Services Offered to Public Nov. 1971 [orig.], 159765 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - ABMC Form #54, Order for Floral decoration at Lorraine American Cemetery [blank] Feb. 1980 [orig.], 159766 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - ABMC Form #49, Photo Request Form [completed] Feb. 1980 [orig.], 159767 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - ABMC Form #51, Revised Price List for Floral Decoration at Lorraine American Cemetery April 7, 1987 [orig.], 159768 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - ABMC Memorial Service program at Lorraine American Cemetery May 24, 1987 [orig.], 159769 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - ABMC Brochure, Lorraine American Cemetery and Memorial April 27, 1988 [date hand-written] [orig.], 159770 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Pamphlet, American Cemetery at Saint Avold, Moselle April 27, 1988 [date hand-written] [orig.], 159771 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Subseries C: Photographs, Personal and Military (1942-1945), 159690
    - Sub-subseries 1: Personal, 1942-1944, 159691
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes 1942, 159692 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform at Camp Crowden, MO March 1, 1942, 159693 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes with Lucille McPherson, Glendale, CA June 13, 1942(?) or 3(?), 159694 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes in Beaumont TX 1943, 159695 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with brother Robert Debes in Beaumont TX 1943, 159696 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Movie stars Georgia Carroll and Bunny Waters in Victorville CA June 5, 1943, 159697 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with movie star Bunny Waters in Victorville CA June 5, 1943, 159698 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Movie star Susan Hayward in Victorville CA May 22, 1943, 159699 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with movie star Georgia Carroll in Victorville CA May 22, 1943, 159700 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes and sister Beatrice Jamail in Pueblo CO 1943, 159701 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes and friend "Lt. Smith" in Beaumont TX 1944, 159702 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Family Group: Vahiba Debes, George Jamail (brother-in-law), Beatrice Jamail, Robert Debes, Jerry Debes in uniform in Beaumont TX 1944, 159703 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes 1944, 159704 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Vahiba Debes and Robert "Bobby" Debes, 159705 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Beatrice Jamail and Robert "Bobby" Debes 1944, 159706 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform [n.d.], 159707 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Jerry Debes in uniform with Lucille McPherson (?) [n.d.], 159708 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Signed portraits of Jane Young in bomber jacket and pilot cap (2) [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Military 1942-1945, 159709
      - Jerry Debes' bomber (plane) in Pueblo CO Oct. 10, 1943, 159710 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Jerry Debes and Crew in England, July 1944 [identification note attached], 159711 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Jerry Debes and his crew 39-7-88 in front of the "Agony Wagon"? [n.d.], 159712 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Jerry Debes grave, Lorraine American Cemetery [n.d.], 159713 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Color photos [6], Jerry Debes Display at Lone Star Flight Museum [1995?], 159714 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Color photos [7], Roll of Honor and American Memorial Chapel, St. Paul's Cathedral London August 1996, 159715 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Unknown bomber squad with name IDs on back [n.d.], 159716 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Allan Gallier and plane [n.d.], 159717 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Aerial photo: Bomb hit on unidentified ship from 12,000 feet [n.d.], 159718 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Aerial photo: Unidentified Power Plant on a Highway at Bridge [n.d.], 159719 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Aerial photo: Unidentified Dam with snowy background from 12,000 feet [n.d.], 159720 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Negatives (4), 159721 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Documents, 1930 and 1944, 159722
        - Page to a missing photograph of Jerry Debes plane, taken Aug. 16, 1944, 159723 (Box 1, Folder 49)
        - Page to a missing photograph of Debes and Fadal families, Beaumont TX June 15, 1930, 159724 (Box 1, Folder 49)
        - Envelopes (2) addressed to Dr. Robert Debes, 159725 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Subseries D: Memorabilia, 1945-1949, 159726
    - Certificates [2], Purple Heart Aug. 31, 1945, 159727 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Jerry Debes Calling cards, 159728 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Tribute Certificate signed by President Harry Truman [unidentified], 159729 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - US Army Air Force's Air Medal and case, 159730 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - US Army Purple Heart medal and case, 159731 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - WWII Military dog tags, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Series II: Debes Investigation and Memorials, 159664
  - Subseries A: Correspondence (1984-2000), 159665
    - Dr. Debes Statement [n.d.], 159666 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Contact Lists [I orig.], 159667 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letter, Elizabeth Knapp to Robert Debes June 26, 1984, 159668 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Quartermaster General, U.S. Army July 1988 [orig.], 159669 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Charlie Freudenthal to Robert Debes July 1988 – July 2000 [several orig.], 159670 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chapters, Charles Fredenthal's History of 489th Bombardment Group, 8th Air Force [unpub.], 159671 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Headquarters U.S. Air Force Aug. 1988 [orig.], 159672 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Senator Lloyd Bentsen to Robert Debes, Aug. to Oct., 1988 [orig.], 159673 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letter and Receipt, National Archives to Robert Debes, Aug. 19, 1988 [orig.], 159674 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Missing Crew Report, 489th Bombardment Group U.S. Army Headquarters Sept. 29, 1944, 159675 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Air Force Historical Research Center Aug. 1988 – June 1996 [many orig.], 159676 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Eighth Air Force Historical Society July 1988 – May 1994 [some orig.], 159677 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Article, "The Dragon and His Tail", Robert Mulcahy [unidentified and n.d.], 159678 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries B: Debes Family Memorials and Donations, 159679
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Congressman Bill Archer May 1995 [orig.], 159680 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to US President George W. Bush, June 1996 [1 orig.], 159681 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Philip McKenna, Office of Defense Attaché, American Embassy, London June 1996 [2 orig.], 159682 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Dean's Office, St. Paul's Cathedral June-Aug. 1996 [orig.], 159683 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, Robert Debes to Joseph Caver, Archivist, Air Force Historical Research Agency May 1994 – May 2011 [some orig.], 159684 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Letter, St. Jude's Children's Research Hospital to Robert Debes May 27, 1994 [orig.], 159685 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Deed of Gift and Inventory, Robert Debes to Lone Star Flight Museum June 1994 – July 1995 [orig.], 159686 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper clipping, Beaumont Enterprise, June 12, 1994 [1 orig.], 159687 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letter, Ira Gruber to Robert Debes, June 26, 1994 [orig.], 159688 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Letter, Alixa Naff to Robert Debes March 22, 1996, 159689 (Box 2, Folder 23)